Guide to the Radio Haiti Papers, circa 1934-2003, bulk 1968-2003 RL.11499
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Government and Politics, 1977-2003
  - Elections, 1979-2003
    - 1990 elections (13 of 13), 1990-1991; 1 folder (Box 61)
    - 1990 elections: results, 1991; 2 folders (Box 58)
      The CEP's results of the 16 December 1990 elections from throughout Haiti.
    - 1995 elections (1-5 of 16), 5 folders (Box 61)
      See also: Préval
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the 1995 presidential and legislative elections. Includes electoral violence and insecurity, irregularities, voting stations and election results throughout regions of Haiti, international observers and support (MINUHA, United States, OAS), the CEP's 1995 Loi Électorale, press releases from several candidates, and other topics.
    - 1995 elections (6-11 of 16), 6 folders (Box 62)
    - 1995 elections (12-16 of 16), 5 folders (Box 63)
    - OAS (Organization of American States), 1995; 1 folder (Box 63)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about Organization of American States (OAS/OEA) observation and support of the 1995 elections in Haiti.
    - General, 1996-1998; 6 folders (Box 64)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the 1997 parliamentary and municipal elections, the 1997 electoral crisis, OAS and IFES (International Foundation for Electoral Systems) involvement in the Haitian electoral process.
    - Pre-Election (1-7 of 11), 1999; 7 folders (Box 65)
      See also: Aristide; Crisis; Organisations populaires
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the 1999 lead-up to the 2000 elections. Includes the Conseil Electoral Provisoire (CEP) under Léon Manus, the Réseau National d'Observateur Electoral (RENO), Fanmi Lavalas, opposition parties, grassroots and civil society groups.
    - Pre-Election (8-11 of 11), 1999; 4 folders (Box 66)
    - Elections 2000 (1-2 of 18), 1999-2000; 2 folders (Box 66)
      See also: Aristide; Crisis; Organisations populaires; IRI
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the contested 2000 parliamentary elections (21 May 2000 and 9 July 2000) and presidential elections (26 November 2000). Includes the Conseil Electoral Provisoire (CEP) and the Loi Électorale 1999; objections by the OAS Electoral Commission; election results throughout the country; irregularities and controversy; conflicts, violence and demonstrations; the assassination of Ferdinand Dorvil; Fanmi Lavalas; OPL; opposition parties including Espace Concertation; international reactions to the elections; the International Republican Institute (IRI); reactions from civil society groups.
    - Elections 2000 (3-9 of 18), 1999-2000; 7 folders (Box 67)
    - Elections 2000 (10-16 of 18), 1999-2000; 7 folders (Box 68)
    - Elections 2000 (17-18 of 18), 1999-2000; 2 folders (Box 69)
    - OAS - Elections, 1999-2001; 2 folders (Box 69)
      See also: Aristide; Crisis
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the Organization of American States (OAS)'s election monitoring mission and response to the 2000 elections.
    - OAS - Elections, 2002; 3 folders (Box 69)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the Organization of American States (OAS)'s election monitoring mission and response to the 2000 elections, particularly OAS Resolutions 806 and 822, intended to help resolve the electoral crisis.
    - CEP, electoral crisis, 2001-2003 (bulk 2002-2003); 1 folder (Box 70)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the Conseil Électoral Provisoire (CEP) and the ongoing electoral crisis, reactions of civil society organizations including NCHR.
  - Parliament, 1991-2003
    - General, 1991; 3 folders (Box 70)
      See also: Aristide
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the 45th legislature under President Jean-Bertrand Aristide and Prime Minister René Préval. Includes the CEP's results of the general elections, army and police, the former head of the CEP Marc André Noël's objection to the Senate's appointments to the Cour de Comptes, and other subjects.
    - Budget, 1991-1998; 1 folder (Box 70)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the parliament's budget process.
    - General (1-2 of 13), 1995-1999; 2 folders (Box 70)
      See also: Political crisis; Conflict with 46th legislature
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the 46th legislature. Includes conflict between the legislative and executive branch under René Préval in 1999. Folders are arranged by year.
    - General (3-9 of 13), 1995-1999; 7 folders (Box 71)
    - General (10-13 of 13), 1995-1999; 4 folders (Box 72)
    - General (1-3 of 5), 2000-2003; 3 folders (Box 72)
      See also: Assassination of Marc-André Dirogène
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the 47th legislature.
    - General (4-5 of 5), 2000-2003; 2 folders (Box 73)
  - Political parties, 1978-2003
    - ALAH (Alliance pour la libération et l'avancement d'Haïti), 1996-1999; 2003; 1 folder (Box 73)
      Radio Haiti materials materials and external materials related to ALAH (Alliance pour la libération et l'avancement d'Haïti) and its leader Reynold Georges.
    - ANDP (Alliance nationale pour la démocratie et le progrès), 1989-1991; 1 folder (Box 73)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the ANDP (Alliance nationale pour la démocratie et le progrès).
    - BIP (Blòk Inite Patriyotik), 1987-1988; 1 folder (Box 73)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the coalition BIP (Blòl Inite Patriyotik), makde up of MNP-28 represented by Déjean Bélizaire, PANPRA represented by André Brutus, and PNDPH represented by Turneb Delpé.
    - CED (Comité d'Entente Démocratique), 1988; 1 folder (Box 73)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the opposition coalition CED (Comité d'Entente Démocratique), made up of Gérard Gourgue of the Front National de Concertation, Marc Bazin of MIDH, and Louis Déjoie II of PAIN. Includes the 1988 general strike against the military government.
    - Coalitions, 1986-1990; 1 folder (Box 73)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to coalitions of political parties. Includes the Assemblée de Concertation; the Concertation Nationale et Démocratique en Haïti (CONCORDH) made up of PNT, MACH, ALAH, and MOP; the Centre Démocratique made up of MIDH, PNT, RDNP, PSCH, PAIN, PAHPAM, MDU, MODELH; the Bloc Démocratique made up of UPD, PDCH, PAIN, and several other parties; the Rassemblement National made up of several political parties and labor unions; and the CLF (Coalition pour la Lutte Finale) made up of the PDCH, RDC, PPNH, and PUNH.
    - Espas Konsètasyon, 1999; 1 folder (Box 73)
      See also: Fanmi Lavalas; Préval; Organisations populaires
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the Espas Konsètasyon/Espace de Concertation, a coalition of political parties formed in opposition to President René Préval and Fanmi Lavalas amid the 1999 political crisis.
    - Fanmi Lavalas, 1996-2002; 3 folders (Box 73)
      See also: Aristide; Préval; OPL; FNCD; Espas Konsètasyon; Organisations populaires
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to Fanmi Lavalas and presidents Jean-Bertrand Aristide and René Préval. Also includes material related to Lafanmi Selavi.
    - FNCD (Front National pour le Changement et la Démocratie), 1990-1991; 1995-1999; 2 folders (Box 74)
      See also: Aristide; OPL; Fanmi Lavalas; 1990 Elections.
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the FNCD (Front National pour le Changement et la Démocratie). Includes, among other subjects, 1990's Operation Lavalas, Jean-Bertrand Aristide's Projet de Société, OP Lavalas, Turneb Delpé and Evans Paul.
    - Front National de Concertation, 1987; 1 folder (Box 74)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the Front National de Concertation and its leader, Gérard Gourgue.
    - KID (Komite Inite Demokratik), 1986-2002; 2 folders (Box 74)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to KID (Komite Inite Demokratik) and leader Evens Paul (K-Plim). Includes the arrest of Jean-Paul Duperval (1986).
    - KONAKOM (Komite Nasyonal Kongrè Mouvman Demokratik), 1987-1997; 4 folders (Box 74)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to KONAKOM (Komite Nasyonal Kongrè Mouvman Demokratik or Comité National du Congrès des Mouvements Démocratiques) and its leader Victor Benoît.
    - KONAKOM (Komite Nasyonal Kongrè Mouvman Demokratik), 1998-2002; 1 folder (Box 75)
    - KOREGA (Kòwòdinasyon Rezistans Grandans), 1995-2001; 1 folder (Box 75)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the KOREGA (Kòwòdinasyon Rezistans Grandans), including various arrests, relations to Lavalas.
    - MDN (Mobilisation pour le Développement National), 1983-1988; 2 folders (Box 75)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the MDN (Mobilisation pour le Développement National) and its founder, Hubert de Ronceray.
    - MDN (Mobilisation pour le Développement National), 1989-2002; 1 folder (Box 75)
    - MIDH (Mouvement Pour la l'Instauration de la Démocratie en Haïti), 1986-1988; 2 folders (Box 75)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials realted to the MIDH (Mouvement Pour la l'Instauration de la Démocratie en Haïti) and party leader Marc Bazin.
    - MIDH (Mouvement Pour la l'Instauration de la Démocratie en Haïti), 1988-2001; 2 folders (Box 76)
    - Miscellaneous, 1985-1990; 2 folders (Box 76)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to a variety of political parties. These include: Parti Populaire Social Chrétien Rénové, Parti d'Union Nationale d'Haïti (PUNH), the Duvalierist political party Parti Nationaliste Progressiste (PNP), Parti de l'Unite Nationale pour le Développement (PUND), La Renaissance d'Haïti, the Rassemblement Démocrate Chrétien, the Mouvement Démocratique de l'Unité (MDU), the Union Nationale des Forces Démocratiques (UNFD), the Parti Réformiste Haïtien, the Union pour le Renouveau Haïtien (URH), the Mouvement d'Union Révolutionnaire (MUR), the Alliance Pour la Renaissance d'Haïti (ARH), the Parti Haïtien de Dieu (PARADIS), the Parti Nationaliste Haïtien, the Union Nationale pour la Defense de la Démocratie et des Droits de l'Homme (UNDDDH), Front Daniel Fignolé Ouvriers Paysans, and others.
    - Miscellaneous, 1995-1999; 2 folders (Box 76)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to a variety of political parties and coalitions. These include: Génération 2004, Ranfò, the Parti Populaire National/Assamblée Populaire Nationale (PPN and APN, under Ben Dupuy), the Groupe de Concertation pour la Conférence Nationale Haïtienne, and others.
    - Miscellaneous, 2001-2003; 1 folder (Box 76)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to a variety of political parties and coalitions. These include: Génération 2004, the PPN, Mouvement Chrétien pour une Nouvelle Haïti (MOCHRENHA), the Union Patriotique, and others.
    - MNP (Mouvement Nationale Patriotique du 28 Novembre), 1989-1991; 1 folder (Box 76)
      Radio Haiti script and press releases about the MNP (Mouvement Nationale Patriotique du 28 Novembre) and leaders Déjean Bélizaire and Max Péan.
    - MODELH-PRDH (Mouvement Démocratique de Libération d'Haïti - Parti du Rassemblement Démocratique d'Haïti), 1988-1991; 1 folder (Box 76)
      Press releases from MODELH-PRDH (Mouvement Démocratique de Libération d'Haïti - Parti du Rassemblement Démocratique d'Haïti) and its leader François Latortue.
    - MOP (Mouvement d'Organisation du Pays), 1986-1999; 3 folders (Box 76)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to MOP (Mouvement d'Organisation du Pays/Mouvman Òganizasyon Peyi a), including Daniel Fignolé, Raoul Peck, ruptures within the party, and the 1989 alliance with MDN and PAIN.
    - MRN (Mouvement pour la reconstruction nationale), 1990; 1995-1997; 1 folder (Box 77)
      See also: PUCH
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the MRN (Mouvement pour la reconstruction nationale) under René Théodore and, later, Rony Mondestin. Includes conflict with PUCH.
    - OPL (Organisation Politique Lavalas/Organisation du Peuple en Lutte), 1995-2002 (bulk 1995-1999); 3 folders (Box 77)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to OPL -- originally Organisation Politique Lavalas, later Organisation du Peuple en Lutte.
    - PAIN (Parti Agricole Industriel National), 1982-1998; 2 folders (Box 77)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the PAIN (Parti Agricole Industriel National) and its leader, Louis Déjoie II.
    - PANPRA (Parti nationaliste progressiste révolutionnaire haïtien), 1987-1991; 1995-1998; 2 folders (Box 77)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to PANPRA (Parti nationaliste progressiste révolutionnaire haïtien).
    - PDCH (Parti Démocrate Chrétien Haïtien), 1978-1984; 2 folders (Box 77)
      See also: Sylvio Claude trials
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the PDCH (Parti Démocrate Chrétien Haïtien) and its founder, Sylvio Claude. Includes the trial and conviction of Sylvio Claude, his liberation, letter from Marie France Claude to Colonel Jean Valmé (1980), various communiqués from the party, support for Claude from human rights groups, pleas from Claude's family.
    - PDCH (Parti Démocrate Chrétien Haïtien), 1986-1987; 3 folders (Box 78)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the PDCH (Parti Démocrate Chrétien Haïtien) and its founder, Sylvio Claude.
    - PDCH (Parti Démocrate Chrétien Haïtien), 1988-1991; 2 folders (Box 78)
    - PLB (Pati Louvri Barye), 1996-2002; 1 folder (Box 78)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the PLB (Pati Louvri Barye) under the leadership of Renaud Bernadin.
    - PNDPH (Parti National Démocratique Progressiste d'Haiti), 1986-1990; 1995-2002; 1 folder (Box 78)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the PNDPH (Parti National Démocratique Progressiste d'Haiti) and its founder Turneb Delpé.
    - PNT (Parti National des Travailleurs), 1987-1990; 1 folder (Box 78)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the PNT (Parti National des Travailleurs) and party leader Thomas Désulmé.
    - PPNH/Bernard Sansaricq, 1986-1990; 1 folder (Box 78)
      See also: Duvalierism and Macoutism; Alain Rocourt to Serge Juste; Life and death of Richard Brisson
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials on Bernard Sansaricq and his Parti Populaire National Haïtien (PPNH). External materials include news, and PPNH press releases and publications.
    - PREN (Parti du Rassemblement pour l'Entente Nationale), 1986-1987; 1 folder (Box 78)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the neo-Duvalierist political party PREN (Parti du Rassemblement pour l'Entente Nationale). Includes denunciations and open letters from several grassroots groups.
    - PROP (Pouvwa Rasanbleman Òganizasyon Popilè), 1995-1998; 1 folder (Box 78)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to PROP (Pouvwa Rasanbleman Òganizasyon Popilè).
    - PSCH (Parti Social Chrétien d'Haïti), 1980-1988; 1 folder (Box 79)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the PSCH (Parti Social Chrétien d'Haïti) and party leader Grégoire Eugène.
    - PUCH (Parti Unifié des Communistes Haitiens), 1978-1991; 1995; 2 folders (Box 79)
      See also: MRN
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to PUCH (Parti Unifié des Communistes Haitiens), including René Théodore, Gérard Pierre-Charles, Max Bourjolly, Suzy Castor, Paul Laraque, and Pierre Clitandre.
    - RDNP (Rassemblement des Démocrates Nationaux Progréssistes), 1980-1988; 2 folders (Box 79)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the RDNP (Rassemblement des Démocrates Nationaux Progréssistes) and the party's leader, Leslie Manigat.
    - RDNP (Rassemblement des Démocrates Nationaux Progréssistes), 1989-2002; 2 folders (Box 79)
    - Tensions, 1990; 1998; 1 folder (Box 79)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to tensions between and within political parties. Includes Pierre Narcisse Maxi's denunciation of Lavalas-Macoute alliances (1998) and conflict between OP17 (Marino Étienne and Patrick Beauchard) and Chavannes Jean-Baptiste of the Mouvman Peyizan Papay (1990)
    - UPN/UPD (Union des Patriotes Nationalistes/Union des Patriotes Démocrates), 1986-1990; 1996; 1 folder (Box 79)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the UPN (Union des Patriotes Nationalistes) which later became the UPD (Union des Patriotes Démocrates) and its coordinator, Rockefeller Guerre.
    - URN (Union pour la Réconciliation Nationale), 1988-1990; 2 folders (Box 79)
      See also: Lafontant coup d'état
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to URN (Union pour la Réconciliation Nationale) and its leader, Roger Lafontant
  - Préval, 1996-2001
    - Bilans, 1996; 4 folders (Box 80)
      Radio Haiti's weekly summaries/assessments of activities of René Préval's government.
    - General (1-2 of 4), 1996; 2 folders (Box 80)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about René Préval's presidency. Includes agrarian reform, international relations and travel abroad (including the OAS Summit on Sustainable Development in Santa Cruz, Bolivia), policy, budget, and other topics.
    - General (3-4 of 4), 1996; 2 folders (Box 81)
    - R. Smarth, 1996-1997; 2 folders (Box 81)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about policy actions by Prime Minister Rosny Smarth and the Haitian parliament under Smarth's leadership.
    - Ericq Pierre, 1997; 1 folder (Box 81)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the failed nomination of Ericq Pierre as Prime Minister.
    - General (1 of 2), 1997; 1 folder (Box 81)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about René Préval's presidency. Includes policy, budget, infrastructure, travels within Haiti and abroad, the political crisis and negotiations, and other topics.
    - General (2 of 2), 1997; 1 folder (Box 82)
    - Bilans, 1997; 1 folder (Box 82)
      Radio Haiti's summaries/assessments of René Préval's government in 1997. Includes politics, international relations, refugee rights, parliament, and justice.
    - Arrest of Léon Jeune, 1997; 1 folder (Box 82)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the arrest of presidential candidate Léon Jeune.
    - Hervé Denis, 1997-1998; 1 folder (Box 82)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the nomination of and failure to ratify Hervé Denis as prime minister.
    - Bilans, 1998; 1 folder (Box 82)
      Radio Haiti's summaries/assessments of René Préval's government in 1998. Includes parliament, security, justice, police, the political crisis, diplomatic relations, and other topics.
    - General, 1998; 1 folder (Box 82)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about René Préval's presidency. Includes policy, budget, the political crisis, infrastructure, travels within Haiti and abroad, and other topics.
    - Political crisis (1 of 3), 1998-1999; 1 folder (Box 82)
      See also: Fanmi Lavalas; OPL; Organisations populaires
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the ongoing political crisis.
    - Political crisis (2-3 of 3), 1998-1999; 2 folders (Box 83)
    - J.E. Alexis, 1998-2000; 1 folder (Box 83)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about policy and actions by Prime Minister Jacques Édouard Alexis and the Haitian parliament under Alexis's leadership.
    - Conflict with 46th legislature, 1999; 1 folder (Box 83)
      See also: Parliament; Political crisis
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the conflict between the 46th legislature and the executive branch.
    - Bilans, 1999; 1 folder (Box 83)
      Radio Haiti's summaries/assessments of the government of René Préval. Includes social movements (particularly strikes), government, police and security, justice, elections.
    - General (1-2 of 5), 1999; 2 folders (Box 83)
      See also: Fanmi Lavalas
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about René Préval's presidency. Includes the ongoing political crisis (including church reactions to the crisis), visits abroad (including Cuba), US relations (including IRI), the assassination of Yvon Toussaint, UN missions in Haiti, Fanmi Lavalas, the Espas Konsètasyon, Initiative Démocratique, OPL, grassroots groups including MPP and women's groups, CARICOM.
    - General (3-5 of 5), 1999; 3 folders (Box 83)
    - General, 2000; 3 folders (Box 84)
      See also: Fanmi Lavalas; Organisations populaires
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about René Préval's presidency, including political crisis, multilateral aid (IADB, IMF), US relations, the Pliché incident in which local Lavalas officials broke up a church meeting, and other topics.
    - Coup d'état attempt, October 2000, 1 folder (Box 84)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the coup d'état plot by police chiefs including Guy Philippe, against Lavalas leaders including Dany Toussaint.
    - General, 2001; 1 folder (Box 84)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the end of René Préval's term and the political situation in general.
  - Provisional governments, 1986-2002
    - November 7, 1986 march, 1 folder (Box 85)
      See also: Anti-CNG protests; Democratic movement
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the November 7, 1986 pro-democracy, anti-Macoute march.
    - Economy - CNG, 1986; 1 folder (Box 85)
      Newspapers and press release about economic matters and the Ministry of Finance during the CNG era.
    - Anti-CNG protests, 1986-1987; 1 folder (Box 85)
      See also: November 7, 1986 march; Democratic movement
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about demonstrations and strikes against the Conseil National de Gouvernement from October 1986 to February 1987.
    - Conseil Consultatif, 1986-1987; 1 folder (Box 85)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the Conseil Consultatif under the direction of Norbert Montero, who was later accused of repressing peasant farmers in Savanette.
    - Namphy (1-5 of 6), 1986-1988; 5 folders (Box 85)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the Conseil National de Gouvernement under General Henri Namphy. Includes army repression, the role of Williams Régala, resistance by the democratic movement and grassroots groups.
    - Namphy (6 of 6), 1986-1988; 1 folder (Box 86)
    - Repression under military government, 1986-1988; 2 folders (Box 86)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about repression by the military government/CNG, including the MJL's reaction to the Labadie massacre, the Fwon Ini nan Gonayiv (FIG) and resistance to Colonel Gambetta Hyppolite in Gonaïves, the arrest of Pollux Saint-Jean, FEDKKA, Djo Lucie.
    - Regional democratic associations, 1986-1989; 2 folders (Box 86)
      See also: Strikes and demonstrations; Repression under military government
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about resistance to the military government by democratic associations and popular organizations throughout Haiti. These include incidents in Port-au-Prince, Léogâne, and Labadie. Associations include the Assemblé Nationale des Organisations Populaires (ANOP), Mouvement des Jeunes de Labadie (MJL), and the Fédération nationale des étudiants haïtiens (FENEH). )
    - Comité de Liaison des Forces Démocratiques, 1986-1989; 1 folder (Box 86)